Guide to the Bureau of Applied Social Research records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Reports
  - Appeals to the Near and Middle East Siegfried Kracauer, 1952, ( 56 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0370-19)
    [This report brings together and codifies the implications of the entire communications behavior study (B-0370) which are most relevant for the International Information Administration's program in the Near and Middle East. The three parts of this report make suggestions for the handling of the media along the Soviet periphery, deal with the content and presentation of the IIA communications and discuss the best ways of communicating with different nationality groups.]
  - Jeannette Green and Babette Kass Brand Motivations in the Purchase of Major Household Appliances-A Pilot Investigation, 1950, (176 pp.; 13 folders containing Television interview, Questionnaires, Empty folder (report- copy in Vienna), Store observations, Misc. materials, Memos & correspondence, the working house study; Electrical & gas home appliance industry, Study, Research proposals) (Box 118, Folder B-0371)
    [100 pilot interviews, 28 observations of actual shopping behavior, with particular reference to refrigerators and television sets. Main objectives were to find some major problems in this area, to discover hypotheses, to test further procedures. Questionnaires included.]
  - Babette Kass The Influence of Handwriting on School Grades, 1950, (34 pp.; 5 folders containing Memos & correspondence, Handwriting & jobs, Test study, Research proposals, Report (2 copies)) (Box 118, Folder B-0372)
    [250 high school students' essays in their own handwriting were graded, then regraded when all were rewritten in uniform mechanical script.]
  - Jeannette Green Preliminary Hypotheses on Factors Affecting the Acceptance of Soluble Coffee, 1949, (234 pp.; 1 folder containing Empty folder (report copy in Vienna)) (Box 118, Folder B-0373)
    [15 depth interviews conducted to find out resistances to soluble coffee and the bases for those resistances and also to determine the factors contributing to its acceptance. Complete interviews included.]
  - Marie Jahoda Talking it Over-An Approach to the Improvement of Inter-Group Relations in Industry, 1949, (51 pp.; 1 folder containing Empty folder (report copy in Vienna)) (Box 118, Folder B-0374)
    [An exploratory study based on data from observations of discussion sessions among 9 management and 15 labor persons at General Cable, Perth Amboy, New Jersey, from informal conversation, answers to questionnaires, and from group evaluation of the course. Questionnaires included.]
  - J. Mayone Stycos and Warren Breed The Harrisburg Community and its Newspapers-An Exploratory Investigation, 1950, (68 pp.; 4 folders containing Questionnaire, Empty folder (report copy in Vienna), Preliminary proposal, Respondents) (Box 118, Folder B-0375)
    [Overall problem was: Do people want another newspaper? 46 personal, unstructured interviews on general climate of Harrisburg to set up hypotheses, to find direction for solution of problem, to develop techniques for its solution.]
  - Stanley Bigman The "New Internationalism" Under Attack, 1950, (105 pp.; 1 folder containing Report) (Box 118, Folder B-0376)
    [Six publications conducting a sustained campaign against world federalism as one aspect of a Communist conspiracy were analyzed as to the arguments used in opposing "World Government."]
  - Kass Margarine Study, 1949, (3 folders containing Interview guide, Questionnaire, Study) (Box 118, Folder B-0377)
  - Lazarsfeld Stock Exchange Study, 1949, (2 folders containing Questionnaire, Proposal) (Box 118, Folder B-0378)
  - Ohio State University Election..., 1949, (1 folder containing Questionnaire) (Box 118, Folder B-0380)
  - Robert Merton Social Theory & Structure, 1949, (1 folder containing Empty folder) (Box 118, Folder B-0385)
  - Fred Ikle The Effect of Physical Destruction in Cities upon Population Size and Distribution, 1951, (93 pp.; 16 folders containing; 6 stapled folders containing, 2 uncovered stapled folders containing Dissertation by Ikle..., Uncovered folder- University report on Human Resource Research Institute, Interview methodology, Interview bibliography, Progress report by Kingsley Davis, Memos & correspondence, Index of reports, Content code for index, Report summary, ...reports & articles, Progress reports- Ikle,) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-1)
    [Using data obtained primarily from more than 60 West German cities bombed in World War 11, this report establishes a method for estimating the population loss of a city as a result of housing destruction.]
  - The Use of Demographic and Transit Data for Urban Analysis: Warsaw as an Illustrative Case. Fred C. Ikle, 1951, ( 31 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-2)
    [Using data obtained primarily from the local statistical office in Warsaw, this report illustrates the use of demographic and transit data in analyzing the growth and development of war-damaged cities.]
  - The Long-Range Effect of Destruction upon Urban Population Distribution Compared with the Short-Range Effect: Hamburg as an Illustrative Case. Fred Ikle, 1951, ( 7 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-3)
    [This report discusses the influence of wartime urban destruction on population distribution as compared to the long-range historical trend in population distribution.]
  - Eleanor Bernert and Fred Ikle Evacuation and the Cohesion of Urban Groups, 1952, (pp.133-136 Published in the Amreican Journal ofSociology, Vol. 58 (1952), pp.133-136.) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-4)
  - The Role of Transportation, Communication and Utilities in the Social Effects of Destruction. Fred Ikle, 1952, ( 31 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-5)
    [This report deals with further problems concerning social effects of air-borne destruction in cities with emphasis on its demographic aspects. It examines the physical effects of destruction on a city's transportation system, communications facilities and utilities in order to determine the social repercussions of this damage.]
  - The Social Effects of Bombing. Fred Ikle. Published. See book: The Social Impact of Bomb Destruction by Fred Ikle. 1950-1952 (Box 118, Folder B-0390-6)
  - The Measurement of Morale. Hilda Hertz, 1951, ( 19 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-7)
    [Purpose of study was "to examine existing studies and literature for techniques of measuring morale, and availability of data useful for the measurement and analysis of morale."]
  - Rank Correlation of Cities and Refinement; Reports 1 & 2. Carl Hammer, 1951, ( 77 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-8,9)
    [Based on statistical data, these reports attempt to develop mathematical formulae for the measurement of degree of urbanization and societal stability.]
  - Growth Rates of the Urban Population: Changes and Their Measurement Carl Hammer and Hilda Hertz, 1952, ( 34 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-10)
    [A discussion of the application of mathematical tools to counts and measurements in urban sociology.]
  - Urbanism: A Summary of the Proceedings of the Columbia University Seminar on Population. A. J. Jaffe, 1951, ( 62 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-11)
    [Discusses the emergence of the modern city in an international context-economic functions performed, identifying characteristics, patterns of land-use, city-region relationships. Suggested research. Bibliography.]
  - Production-Maintenance Functions of the Urban Working Force. A. J. Jaffe, 1951, ( 16 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-12)
    [This is an attempt to differentiate between workers performing production functions and workers performing maintenance functions and a consideration of the implications of such a division. Based on Canadian and U.S. census data.]
  - The Stability of Cities: Some Considerations and Calculations. A. J. Jaffe, 1951, ( 35 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-13)
    [A consideration of the stability of relationships among cities over a period of time, and of the stability of industrial relationships within single cities over a period of time.]
  - A Survey of the Contents of Russian Censuses. Joseph Froomkin, 1951, ( 78 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-14)
    [This paper is concerned with a descriptive survey of the contents of the Russian census describing in detail the census of 1926 and to a lesser extent those of 1897, 1917, 1920, and 1923. An explanation of definitions of terms is included.]
  - A Comparative Study of Skill Designations in the U.S. and U.S.S.R. Joseph Froomkin and A. J. Jaffe, 1952, ( 30 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-15)
    [An attempt to determine whether the difference in definition of skilled workers in the U. S. and U. S. S.R. is related to differences in technological and socioeconomic structures. Based on census data.]
  - Analysis of Effects of Urbanization in Five Russian Cities. Joseph Froomkin, 1952, ( 83 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-16)
    [An enumeration of changes in the technological and socioeconomic structure of five Russian cities which have taken place during rapid urbanization. Includes discussion of usefulness of Soviet statistics.]
  - Estimating a Nation's Urban Growth. A. J. Jaffe, Carl Hammer and Dorothy Jahn, 1952, ( 44 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-17)
    [A discussion of empirical examples of urban growth and alternative means of estimating such growth.]
  - Korean Urbanization: Past Development and Future Potentials. Thomas 0. Wilkinson, 1952, ( 87 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-18)
    [This study is an attempt to provide some pertinent information about the socioeconomic development of Korea and to relate such development to the growth of Korean cities. Based on census data.]
  - World Urban Resources Index, Progress Report. Kingsley Davis, Carl Hammer, Hilda Hertz, Lois Pratt, Samuel Pratt and Natalie Rogoff, 1952, ( 39 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0390-20)
    [A progress report and prospectus for the future of a system for filing quantitative data for the cities of the world with over 100,000 population.]
  - Anticipatory Socialization, A Study of Mobility Expectations and Style of Life. Theresa Falaguerra, 1957, ( 81 pp. ) (Box 118, Folder B-0555-6)
    [This discusses behavioral and attitudinal indicators of expected change in socioeconomic status which appeared in questionnaires administered to car owners in Peoria, Illinois, and San Bernardino, California.]
  - The Universe of Cities: Some Preliminary Considerations. Natalie Rogoff, 1953, ( 34 pp. ) (Box 119, Folder B-0390-21)
    [This report deals with the potential usefulness of the World Urban Resources Index for comparative, systematic analysis and stresses the importance of the context, or universe, of a particular city in such analysis.]
  - Relative Merits of Various Formulas for Rates of Growth. Carl Hammer and Natalie Rogoff, 1952, ( 15 pp. ) (Box 119, Folder B-0390-22)
    [An evaluation of methods of calculation of rates of growth intended for use in large-scale projects.]
  - A Functional Interpretation of the Cost-Utility Index. Carl Hammer, 1952, ( 9 pp. ) (Box 119, Folder B-0390-23)
    [A discussion of operationalizing Otis Dudley Duncan's cost-utility framework.]
  - Demographic Indices of the World's Urban Population. Natalie Rogoff, Bonnie Loflin, Thomas Wilkinson and Samuel Baum, 1953, ( 97 pp. ) (Box 119, Folder B-0390-24)
    [Age structure and sex composition of urban populations. Demographic profiles of some cities. Intercity variation in demographic structure. Based on data on file in World Urban Resources Index.]
  - The Mediterranean Region and its Cities. Donald Foley, Judith Blake, Hilda Hertz and Suzette Kettler, 1953, ( 204 pp. ) (Box 119, Folder B-0390-25)
    [A study of the demographic structure of 94 Mediterranean cities and their economic roles. Based on World Urban Resources Index data.]
  - Kingsley Davis and others Interview Methodology Research Program, 1951, (49 folders containing and 1 binder Air interrogation guide - Airforce (1952, market restricted), List of documents, Project explanation, Project descriptions, Memo, Organizational structure, Plans & requirements, Objective & plans, Cost reimbursement, Expenditures- through June 1951, Statement of plans, Work statement, General proposals, Methodological considerations, Sample preliminary analysis- Harvard Individual reports & articles, Research memorandums, Research program & schedule for German staff, Raw individual intelligence reporter (marked restricted), Questionnaire, Attachments, Memos& correspondence, Wriggens material- 4 separate folders included, Progress reprort,, Article (restricted), Misc., Guide to interviewing voluntary sources (restricted), Exploratory studies in nature of interviewing, Data collection forms, Reports & memos, Harvard Refugee Interview project, Interviewing hints, Bibliography on Columbia University Project, Selection of interviewers, Empty folder (Bibliography o interviewing literature), Proposal for further investigations) (Box 119, Folder B-0391)
    [Vols. I-V, Five volumes are: I. Data Collection Forms and related Material, 28 pp.; II. Reports and Memoranda, 88 pp.; III. The Harvard Refugee Project, 58 pp.; IV. Interviewer Hints for Wringer Interviews, 38 pp.; V. Bibliography of the Literature concerning the use of Interviewing in Selected Fields, 77 p.]
  - J. Mayone Stycos Changes in Razor Blade Brands-A Study of Consumer Motivations, 1950, (58 pp.; 4folders Codes & Questionnaires, Proposal, Memos, Empty folder (report)) (Box 119, Folder B-0392)
    [26 men were intensively interviewed to uncover motivations which might not come out by more standard questionnaire method and to develop a questionnaire which could test and elaborate upon hypotheses developed as a result of the study.]
  - Robert C. Myers Reaction to Toni and Lilt Home Waves, 1951, (155 pp.; 11 folders containing Interview guide, Proposal, Trip report, Studies, Empty folder (report copy in Vienna), Empty folders, Observation summary, Employment applications, Respondent key) (Box 119, Folder B-0393)
    [250 depth interviews in Buffalo of women who had switched from one to the other.]
  - Leo Srole, Babette Kass and Charles Glock I.A.D. Car Card Evaluation Study: Preliminary Draft, 1951, (223 pp.; 12 folders containing ) (Box 119, Folder B-0394-1)
    [This study focussed on the audience for the posters prepared by the Institute for American Democracy and the experiences of the subjects as they saw the material. 400 bus riders in Springfield, Massachusetts, were intensively interviewed using mainly open-ended questionnaires.]
  - Impact of Public Service Advertising: A Controlled Study of Anti-Discrimination Car Cards. Leo Srole, Charles Glock and Babette Kass, 1952, ( 166 pp. ) (Box 119, Folder B-0394-2)
    [Based on 401 interviews with bus riders in Springfield, Massachusetts, this report evaluates audience reaction to a series of posters prepared by the Anti-Defamation League designed to improve attitudes toward minority groups. It discusses such factors as who and how many people saw the posters, and the viewers' comprehension and recall of these posters.]
  - William McPhee, Phillip Ennis and Alan Meyer A Progress Report of the 1950 Congressional Voting Study, 1952, (79 pp.; 14 folders containing Empty folder (McPhee & ...Public Opinion & Congressional Elections), Memos & correspondence, Questionnaires, Articles, Misc. materials, Background material & questionnaires, Article, Codebook, Progress report on study) (Box 119, Folder B-0395)
    [This report includes a progress report on the study of the 1950 Congressional elcctions by William McPhee, and two papers by Philip Ennis and Alan Meyer. Meyer's paper "The Independent Voter" discusses the definition and characteristics of the independent voter, while Ennis's "Contextual Factors in Voting Decisions" examines how differing social and political contexts affect standards of judgement and voting behavior.]
  - Stanley K. Bigman Evaluating the Effectiveness of U.S.I.E. Programs: A Manual on Research Methods and Techniques, 1951, (298 pp.; 3 folders containing Questionnaire, Empty folder (Report-copy in Vienna), State Department manual- How Important is an Information Program?) (Box 119, Folder B-0396)
    [A manual for public affairs officers on how to run an evaluational research project: opinion leaders, obtaining representative sample, questionnaire construction, interviewing techniques and interviewer selection, use of panels, observation and participant observer, and analyzing the content of communications.]
  - Lipset, Trow, Coleman Union Democracy (International Typographical Union Study), 1950, (7 folders containing Codebook and marginals. Questionnaires, Proposals, Non-bureau code guide, Interviewer instructions, Article, Review) (Box 119, Folder B-0400)
  - Kass What Does Your Congregation Think?, 1950, (1 folder containing Monograph) (Box 119, Folder B-0402)
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld Methodological Considerations in International Broadcasting Research, 1951, (181 pp. 3 Folders. Project contract, Memos & corespondence, Report ) (Box 119, Folder B-0404)
    [Methodological considerations include: opinion leadership comparison in urban-rural Sweden; the snowball technique; identifying international audience; Voice of America audience in Norway; content analysis and "competitive broadcasting" to Germany; testing Voice of America programs; latent content of broadcasts.]
  - Robert O Carlson Case Finding & Patient Management- Through an Understanding of Known Syphilitic Patients, 1950, (1 folder containing Study) (Box 119, Folder B-0405)
  - School of Public Health/ BASR Episdemiology of Hypertension, 1953, (1 folder containing Report- planning and research on episdemiology & unrelated pamphlet) (Box 119, Folder B-0406)
    [Report not available?]
  - Jaffe Manpower & Labor Force Analysis, 1950, (1 folder containing Empty folder (monograph)) (Box 119, Folder B-0407)
  - B.A.S.R. Evaluation of the Proposed Betty Crocker Television Program, 1950, (120 pp.; 18 folders containing Questionnaires, Script of program, Memos & correspondence, Proposal, Syracuse test sessions I-X, Charts & graphs, Tentative report, Preliminary report) (Box 119, Folder B-0409)
    [352 women registered interest in or dislike of the program on the Program Analyzer, answered a questionnaire and took part in group discussion. Questionnaire included. Report not available]
  - Peter H. Rossi Urban Residential Mobility, 1952, (462 pp.20 folders and 1 separate binder. Separate binder contains codes. Folders contain Typed report, Ross's Manuscript, Summary of field work experience, Research & analysis memoranda, Map series-Philadelphia, Structure sampling, Philadelphia Housing & Neighorhood owners questionnaire, Owners and renters questionnaires, Enumeration sheet code, Residential mobility decision analysis, Marginals, Validation of Mobility Potential Scale, Interview schedule, Questionnaire, Proposals for research, Book & AJS article-Why Families Move?) (Box 119, Folder B-0410)
    [Why Families Move, Glencoe, IL: The Free Press, 1955. Inteviews with a stratified sample of approximately 1000 in Philadelphia provided information for this study which focussed on characteristics of mobile and stable areas, characteristics of mobile households, and reasons for moves given by mobile households. Questionnaire and bibliography included.]
  - Kendall Conflict and Mood (Reliability Factor), 1950, (12 fodlers Dissertation, Article, Codes, Empty folder (article), Questionnaires, Questionnaire instructions) (Box 119, Folder B-0411)
  - American Jewish Committee Communication Study, 1950, (2 folders containing Questionnaires, Codebook) (Box 119, Folder B-0412)
  - Merton, Lazarsfeld, Morsell Titl: 1950, ( 2 Folders. Empty folder containing (...in Social Research, Merton & Lazarsfeld), Empty folder containing (S-0418- Doctoral Dissertation on Political Behavior of Negroes in New York City) ) (Box 119, Folder B-0415-1)
  - Paul F. Lazarsfeld and Robert K. Merton Proposal to Establish an Institute for Training in Social Research, 1950, (97 pp.; 40 folders containing ) (Box 120, Folder B-0420-1)
    [This is concerned with the problems of training in empirical social research. It proposes to establish the institute as a significant step towards a more adequate training program.]
  - Training for Social Science Research: A Qualitative Analysis of Factors Affecting the Training of Students for Modern Social Research. Charles R. Wright, 1952, ( 90 pp. ) (Box 120, Folder *B-0420-5-3)
    [Published as part of doctoral dissertation, "The Effects of Training in Social Research on the Development of Professional Attitudes," Ann Arbor: University Microfilms, 1954.]
  - A Formalization of Robert K. Merton's Explanation of "Value Homophily." Paul F. Lazarsfeld, 1953, (41 pp. ) (Box 120, Folder B-0420-3)
    [This paper is an attempt to formalize Merton's theoretical reflections. Merton's analysis of homophily with regard to racial attitudes is presented followed by a formalization of this analysis.]
  - The Construction of Indexes: A Common Language and Framework. S. M. Miller, 1953, (24 pp. ) (Box 10120, Folder B-0420-4)
    [This paper briefly sketches a model of a research procedure and then explores in detail the general procedure followed at the last stages of an investigation.This paper is an attempt to formalize Merton's theoretical reflections. Merton's analysis of homophily with regard to racial attitudes is presented followed by a formalization of this analysis. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Historical Materials on Innovations in Higher Education. Bernhard J. Stem, 1953, (550 pp. ) (Box 120, Folder B-0420-5)
    [This is a collection of examples from the history of higher education where innovations in advanced learning were proposed and either adopted or defeated. The purpose was to obtain information on the conditions under which new institutions become necessary, on how ideas develop into concrete plans, and on the forces that aid or hinder these plans. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - The Panel Technique: As a Systematic Introduction to Through-Time Analysis in the Behavioral Sciences. Joseph A. Precker, 1953, (148 pp. ) (Box 120, Folder B-0420-6)
    [This discussion of panel methods for the investigation of attitudes, and other manifestations of social change, is an attempt to organize some of the major studies and techniques into a consistent developing framework. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Documents for the Seminar on Concepts and Indices in the Social Sciences. Natalie Rogoff, 1953, (301 pp. ) (Box 120, Folder B-0420-7)
    [This is a collection of documents dealing with specification of concepts, formal structure of individual and group characteristics, multi-dimensional classification, attribute space, and derived problems. Case material on specific sociological and economic concepts and specific concepts in social psychology and the measurement of change over time are also discussed. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Concepts and Indices. Edited by Paul F. Lazarsfeld, 1953, (222 pp. ) (Box 120, Folder B-0420-8)
    [This is a collection of documents from the Dartmouth Seminar on Concepts and Indices, July 11-25, 1953. Part I: Organization and Basic Themes; Part II: Documentation of the Leading Themes; Part II, A: From Imagery to Index-A Schematic Sequence, Part II, B: The Basic Operational Problems; Part III: Additional Case Materials and Reports. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Analysis of Social Process. Edited by Paul F. Lazarsfeld, 1954, (459 pp. ) (Box 120, Folder B-0420-9)